In this unit we're going to talk about
the challenge of translating individual
statements or individual instructions
from symbolic to binary code.
Now the general problem that we
are facing is developing an assembler
that translates program from
symbolic hack language,
into binary hack code and
in order to write such an assembler
we have to know how to deal with white
space, instructions and symbols.
Now in order to make our life easier we
decided to defer the treatment of symbols
to a later stage and we also described
previously how to handle white space.
Basically we're going
to ignore white space.
So, what remains, is a program
that contains instructions only,
A-instructions and
C-instructions without symbols.
So, in order to write an assembler that
can translate such a programming to binary
code we have to know how to translate
A-instructions and C-instructions.
And that's exactly what
we're going to discuss next.
So, let us begin with A-instructions.
Here's the general rule and
the syntax rule of how to put together
an A-instruction and an example.
And here's the same,
instruction expressed in the binary code.
Notice that,
the opcode of an A-instruction is zero.
This is the first, red zero bit that you
see, in the example at the bottom right.
By the way,
the colors are completely meaningless,
and I used them only to
improve our communications.
You know,
once it gets into actually implementation,
the colors once again
play no role whatsoever.
So how to translate from symbolic to
binary when it comes to an A-instruction.
Well if you think about it,
the only challenge is to do
something with this value.
So basically if the value
is a decimal constant,
all we have to do is compute the binary
representation of this value.
Add as many zeroes as we need in order
to turn it into a 15 bit constant.
Ed or append, the zero opcode and,
that's what we, and, and that's what is a,
a needed 16 bit, representation of this,
of this instruction.
So it's not a big deal, but
obviously we have to do it.
What if, value's a symbol?
Well, I just want to, remind you,
what what we said earlier.
We're going to,
deal with symbols later on.
So, translating instructions is, is
something that's not terribly complicated,
but once again it takes, some programming.
All right, what about C-instructions.
Well, C-instructions also have a symbolic
manifestation and and
a binary manifestation.
And there's a set of tables, so to speak,
that describe the mapping from.
Symbolic pneumonics into
their binary representations.
So these are the rules of the game when
it comes to translating C-instructions.
So how do you actually do it?
I think the easier way to to describe
the translation process is to
do it using an example.
So suppose we're giving this single
C-instruction and we have to
translate that into binary code.
Well, before we go on I want to
remind you that every C-instruction
consists of three fields.
So, in the example that we have here.
The MD pneumonic is
the destination field or
the value of the destination field
in this particular instruction.
Then comes D plus 1,
which is the value of the comp or
computational, computation field.
And we also have a jump field
which happens to be null.
You know, we don't have a jump
instruction here so the jump is a null.
So implicit in what I'm saying
is the assumption that we can
somehow take this source instruction and
decompose it into these three fields.
And indeed this is something that is going
to be done by an element of our assembler
called parser.
The parser is going to
take a source statement or
instruction written in symbolic code and
chop it into three individual,
individual fields, and then we can inspect
every one of these fields in isolation.
And act on it, and
that's exactly what I'm going to do next.
So, let us begin to,
put together the string of characters
that will end up representing the binary
code of MD equals D plus one.
We can do it in, in many different ways,
and here is one of them.
Focusing on the target expression
we see that every C-instruction
begins with three ones.
When it comes to to the binary
flavor of C-instructions, so
we initialize the string
that we are building.
With three ones.
That's, that's what we
do when we get started.
Next we focus, if we want, we focus on the
next seven bits that we have to create.
And these seven bits
correspond to the comp field.
Now, the comp field
happens to be D plus one.
Once again, I assume that I have access
to this, field, I can easily retrieve it.
I see that it's D plus one.
And if it's D plus one I can look
it up in the relevant table.
I look up this pneumonic, and
I see that it corresponds to, an a bit,
which is zero, and to six control
bits which are zero and five ones.
So putting these bits together I generate
the seven bit value zero
zero one one one one one and
I append it to the string
that I gradually build here.
Alrl ight.
The next thing to do is focus on
the next part of the instruction
which corresponds to the destination.
So, I look up the value
of my destination field.
It happens to be MD.
I consult the relevant, table.
And I see that the MD
pneumonic corresponds to 011.
I take this 011 value, I append it to
this string that I gradually built,
and I've completed the the synthesis
of these two fields together.
Moving along the remaining three bits
correspond to the jump directive.
I look up the value of the jump
directive in my source instruction.
I see that it's null.
I look up null in the relevant table and
I see that it corresponds to
the three bits zero, zero, zero.
I take these bits, append them to
the end of the string and voila,
we have managed to translate the symbolic
instruction into its binary equivalent.
As you see, everything that they
do here is text processing,
and in, in some languages it
is called string processing,
I have a source string which
I analyze in some way and,
I have a target string which I build,
you know, in some gradual process.
And, every high level language
has the capability to
to do such as string processing.
And, that's exactly what you'll do
when you actually write the assembler.
Now, when we say that we
generate binary code.
There may be some misunderstanding here so
let me clarify it.
We basically generate a text
file that contains of
that which is, which consists of two
characters only zero and one but
they are treated as characters as SD or
Unicode characters.
So we have this text file that we write
which consists of zeros and ones only.
And later on we're going to load
this text file into the computer.
And once we load it into the computer it
becomes real zeros and ones so to speak.
All right so this basically concludes.
The translation of C-instructions.
So with that in mind,
here is the overall assembly logic.
We are given a text file, and this text
file contains all sorts of characters
that hopefully represent a Hack
program written in symbolic Hack code.
So, how do we translate it into binary?
Well, we process this file.
And, we begin marching through it.
And for each instruction, or for
each line in this file,
we first of all parse the instruction.
We break it into its underlying fields.
So if we have an A-instruction
we have the at sign and a value.
We take this value and
we re-express it in binary code.
If it's a C-instruction we split
the instruction into its three
fields comp, desk, and
and jump, and also for
every one of these fields we generate the,
corresponding
binary binary bits, and
then we assemble all these codes that we,
created into a single 16 bit instruction.
And we write this instruction
to an output file.
Which is not seen here in the picture.
But, the assembler creates this
empty file at the beginning.
And begins to populate it with, lines.
Each line being a sequence of, or
a string of 16 zeros and ones.
So this is the overall process
of translating a Hack program.
A program that consists of only A and
C-instructions without symbols.
If you do all this,
then you will manage to create
an assembler that can translate
programs into binary code and
everything looks very nice indeed,
and I'd hate to be,
a party spoiler, but there's a big
gap that we haven't closed yet,
and this is the fact that the source
code contains no symbols.
We have managed to to design an assembler
that translates a symbol-less programs,
but we still have to close this
gap of dealing with symbols, and
that's exactly what we're
going to do in the next unit.